嘿
Hey,
各位 今天我们要聊一个越来越重要的非常有趣的话题
everyone. So today we're going to talk about a pretty interesting topic that becomes increasingly
就是关于智能体可观测性你需要了解的一切
important every day, which is everything you need to know about agent observability.
先简单介绍一下我们自己
So a little bit about us.
我是Zubin 是Raindrop的首席执行官兼联合创始人
So I'm Zubin. I'm the CEO and co-founder of Raindrop.
我是Danny 我是Raindrop的后端工程师 也负责大量的SDK相关工作
I'm Danny. So I'm the back-end engineer at Raindrop and I do a bunch of SDK work as well at there.
而Raindrop本质上是帮助AI工程师发现
And Raindrop essentially helps AI engineers find,
追踪并修复生产环境中的智能体问题
track, and fix issues in production agents.
我们也很幸运能和这个领域里一些最有意思的团队合作
And we're lucky to work with some of the most interesting teams in the space as well.
智能体的失败和传统软件中的失败非常不同
Agent failures are very different than traditional failures in software.
智能体是非确定性的
So agents are non-deterministic,
它们是无边界的 你可以输入的内容空间几乎是无限的
they're unbounded, there's an infinite space of inputs that you can put in,
它们能返回的输出空间也几乎是无限的
there's an infinite space of outputs that they can return,
而且它们有时可以调用工具 任意影响其他系统
and they can use tools sometimes to affect other systems arbitrarily.
因此如何处理智能体失败以及如何监控它们
And this problem of agent failures and monitoring them,
并确保我们能够理解这些问题
making sure we can understand them,
随着时间推移只会变得越来越重要
becomes only more important with time.
情况之所以在变糟 是因为
It's getting worse because,
第一 智能体本身越来越复杂
A, agents are getting more complex,
第二 会话可以变得非常长
B, sessions can get longer,
有时智能体可以在没有任何用户输入的情况下连续运行好几个小时
sometimes agents can run for hours and hours without any input from a user.
最后 风险和代价也在不断增大
And then lastly, the stakes are getting bigger and bigger.
这是因为智能体已经被部署在医疗 金融 甚至
This is because agents are being deployed in healthcare and finance and even in the
军事等领域 在这些场景中一旦出错后果会非常灾难性
military, where it's catastrophic if things go wrong.
传统上我们谈论的范式是评估（eval）
The traditional paradigm we've been talking about is evals,
也就是你有一组测试输入 想看看智能体会给出什么样的输出
where you have this sort of test input and you want to see what is the output that comes
看看智能体会产出什么结果
out from the agent.
你会有这样一整套数据
You have a set of these,
你可能会称之为黄金数据集
maybe you call it a golden dataset.
但在这个新的范式下 仅靠评估（eval）已经远远不够
But evals, they just aren't enough with this new paradigm.
随着智能体能力越来越强
As agents become more and more capable,
会出现越来越多有趣但未定义的行为
there's more and more interesting undefined behavior that can happen.
比如 智能体可以从一组不同的工具中进行调用
For example, agents can call from a set of different tools.
有时候工具的数量还在指数级增长
Sometimes the number of tools is growing exponentially.
它们可以调用不同的记忆源
They can call from different memory sources.
它们可以调用自己的子智能体
They can call their own sub-agents,
而这些子智能体又有自己的工具和记忆源
which those sub-agents have their own tools and memory sources,
并且还能递归地再拥有自己的子智能体
and recursively can have their own sub-agents.
随着时间推移 这一切只会变得更加复杂
This is just becoming more complicated with time,
在这种组合爆炸式的输入空间下
and with this combinatorial sort of input space,
仅仅准备一套输入输出测试已经完全不够用了
just having a set of tests for input and output doesn't cut it anymore.
你根本不可能覆盖到你想要的所有边界情况
There's no way you can hit all of the edge cases that you would want to here.
因此我们需要从测试和评估（eval）范式转向监控范式
And so we go from a testing and evals paradigm to a monitoring paradigm.
回想在有智能体之前构建产品时
And if you think of building products before agents,
测试一直都非常重要
testing was always very important.
拥有单元测试等是很重要的
It's important to have your unit tests,
但监控线上生产环境要重要得多
etc., but monitoring production is just infinitely more important,
它能让你迭代更快 并且更好地捕捉长尾问题
and it allows you to move faster and be better at catching the long tail.
我们认为在某种程度上这可能有点争议
And we think in some ways this is kind of controversial,
但我们一直把这称为人类的最后一个问题
but we've been calling this humanity's last problem.
当人类再也无法监控智能体并发现其中的问题时
When humans are no longer able to monitor agents and find issues with them,
那它们就已经远远超前于我们了
then they're just way ahead of where we are.
因此 这是当今时代最重要的问题之一
And so this is one of the most important problems of our time,
就是发现生产环境中的智能体问题
is catching issues in production agents.
要在生产环境中构建可靠的智能体
So to build reliable agents in production,
并确保你能够对它们进行监控
and to make sure you can monitor them,
你需要一套良好的信号体系
you need a good set of signals.
那么 什么是信号呢
So what are signals?
在我们看来 主要有两大类
There's two real types that we think of,
隐式信号和显式信号
implicit signals and explicit signals.
隐式信号更多关注正在发生事情的语义层面
Implicit signals deal with sort of the semantic nature of what's going on,
而显式信号则对应客观现实
and explicit signals deal with objective reality,
也就是那些可以被验证真假的东西
things that are verifiably true or false.
比如 显式信号包括错误率这样的指标
For example, explicit signals are things like error rate.
你确实需要监控你的工具错误率以及其他正在发生的错误
You really want to be monitoring your tool error rate and other errors that are happening,
还有延迟 用户重新生成的次数 或者成本
or latency, or users regenerating, or the cost.
如果这些指标中任何一个突然飙升
If any of these things spike,
比如你看到智能体的错误率突然升高
right, if you're seeing error rates spike in your agent,
通常就意味着某些地方出了问题
that's usually a good sign that something is wrong.
而如果这些指标一直很平
And if you see it flat,
这本身也可能说明一些情况
that could mean something as well.
延迟 重新生成次数和成本也是同样的道理
Same thing with latency, regenerations, or cost.
隐式信号则非常有趣
Implicit signals are interesting,
在我看来甚至更有意思
they're even more interesting in my opinion,
也更难被发现
and even harder to find.
第一类是正则表达式信号
So the first is regex signals,
这个我待会儿会讲到
which I'll come to in a second.
第二类是分类器
The second is classifiers,
最后一类是自诊断
and then the last is self-diagnostics.
我们先来看这类基于分类器的信号
So let's take these sort of classifier signals.
最好的隐式信号是用来检测问题的
The best implicit signals are detecting issues,
它们不一定是以LLM作为评判者 去打分输出
they're not necessarily LLM-as-a-judge, judging outputs.
比如 这个XYZ回复有多好
So for example, how good is XYZ response,
或者请在1到10分之间给ABC打个分
or rate ABC on a scale from 1 to 10?
这些做法远不如你先定义一套非常明确的问题类型
Not as effective as having a very solid set of issues you're looking for,
然后用二元分类器告诉你这些问题的发生率是在上升还是在下降 来得有效
in sort of binary classifiers that are telling you if issue rate is going up or down.
在各种智能体产品中 一些常见且有价值的隐式信号包括拒绝响应
So some common implicit signals that are valuable across agent products are things like refusals.
比如助手会说
So the assistant saying,
我做不到 很抱歉 之类的话
like, I can't do that, I'm sorry.
或者任务失败 某个环节出了问题
Or task failure, where something goes wrong,
导致智能体无法完成任务
and so the agent is unable to complete a task.
用户挫败感 内容审核
User frustration, content moderation,
不适宜内容（NSFW） 越狱 以及一些正向的成功信号
NSFW, jailbreaking, and then you can even have wins.
也就是那些正向的信号
So positive signals as well.
而这些就是
And these are the things that,
Raindrop可以开箱即用地提供给你的东西
like, Raindrop gives you out of the box as well.
不过我先快速给大家展示一下这是什么样子
But let me just show you quickly what this looks like.
比如说 大家都能看到这个吗
For example, can everyone see this?
我把它放大一点
Maybe I'll make it a little bit bigger.
这样你们就能大致感受到
So you can get a sense of,
比如说按天来看，到底是哪些事件在引发用户挫败感
like, day by day, what are sort of the events that are causing user frustration?
我们看到那里有一个激增
We see there's a spike there.
或者任务失败率
Or task failure rate,
懒惰、拒绝响应，这些我们今天也看到在激增
laziness, refusals, which we're also seeing spike today.
拥有一套好的这些信号会对你的产品非常有帮助
And having a good set of these really helps with your product.
你也可以自己来设置这些
You can set these up yourself as well,
或者直接使用我们开箱即用提供的
or we give it out of the box.
那我们来看一下用户挫败感
So let's look at user frustration.
你可以看到这里，好吧，那是不对的
You can see here, okay, that is not correct.
你没说“我保证”，说出来
You didn't say I promise, say it.
或者“你错了，我没问你这个”
Or you're wrong, I didn't ask you that.
你可以在这里看到各种各样的用户挫败感
You can see all sorts of user frustration here.
你还能看到这个比例
And you can see the rate,
每一天的百分比
the percentage every single day.
如果它激增，那就是你非常需要设置告警的东西
If that spikes, it's something you're really gonna want alerting on.
所以你就可以
So you can just, like,
在这里快速添加一个告警
quickly add an alert here.
这是一个用来判断你的智能体随时间变化健康状况的方法
And this is one way to figure out sort of the health of your agent over time.
不仅仅是这些
It's not just that.
正则表达式也可以是一个非常好的信号
Regex can be a very good signal as well.
比如几天前Claude Code的源代码泄露时
So when Claude Code source code leaked a few days ago,
有个很有意思的文件叫user prompt keywords.ts
one thing that was interesting was this user prompt keywords.ts,
它基本上就是
which was basically this,
一长串正则表达式字符串，用来寻找出问题的迹象
like, long Regex string that was looking for indications of stuff going wrong.
“WTF”“这太烂了”“太糟糕了”之类
WTF, this sucks, horrible.
我们都曾对Claude Code说过这种话
We've all been guilty of saying these kinds of things to Claude Code.
所以这是一个非常非常有用的信号
So it's a very, very useful signal.
接下来发生的事情是，这个布尔值is negative会被切换为true
What would happen after that is this boolean is negative was being flipped to true.
然后在每一天以及每一次产品发布之后
And then every single day and after every single product release,
这个挫败感比例都会被持续标记出来
this frustration rate was tagged over time.
这对Claude Code团队来说是一个非常简单的方式来弄清楚
And this was a very easy way for the Claude Code team to figure out,
比如我们做了一个改动后，真实的问题发生率是多少，或者哪里出了问题
like, what is the actual issue rate if we make a change or something going wrong.
而且这就是一种
And it was just, like,
成本非常低的做法
a very cheap way to do that as well.
所以正则表达式非常强大
So Regex is very powerful.
最后一个是实验
The last is experiments.
那当你已经有了一套好的信号之后，你要做什么
So what do you do once you have a set of good signals?
所以首先，就像我之前给你展示的那样
So the first thing is, like I showed you before,
你可以设置告警
you can have alerting.
接下来你可以用它来更快、更好地构建产品
The next thing you can do is you can actually use it to build product faster and better.
做法是这样的
So the way you do it is,
比如说你想发布某个改进或某种修复
let's say you want to ship some improvement or some sort of fix.
你想更换模型
You want to change the model.
你想修改提示词
You want to change prompting.
或者修改智能体框架里的某些东西
Or maybe something about the agent harness.
你想添加一个新工具
You want to add a new tool.
无论你改了什么，你都可以先把它发布给一部分用户
Whatever you change, what you can do is you can ship it to some percentage of users and
然后保留你现有的对照组
then have your additional existing control group.
这样就能很好地帮助你判断
And that gives you a good sense,
当你有了一套好的信号，比如拒绝响应、用户挫败感
once you have a good set of signals, refusals, user frustration,
等等，如果这些问题发生率上升
et cetera, if those issue rates go up,
这些信号发生率在这次发布之后上升
those signal rates go up after this ship,
也就是你发布的这个新东西之后
this new thing you shipped,
那就很能说明你发布的东西其实并不好
that's a good signal that what you shipped is not really good.
这有点像A/B测试
It's sort of like A-B testing,
但用的是我们的语义信号
but using our semantic signals,
以及我们之前提到的那些信号
et cetera, that we talked about earlier.
比如说，在Raindrop里看起来会是这样
So for example, this is what it would look like in Raindrop.
但本质上，比如我发布了一个新的提示词版本，prompt 2.4
But essentially, let's say I ship a new version of the prompt, prompt 2.4.
你可以看到，用户挫败感的比例是多少
You can see, what is the user frustration rate?
它已经大幅下降
It's gone down very substantially.
从37%降到9%，好得多
37% to 9%. It's much better.
关于界面美观或者部署相关问题的抱怨也是一样
Same thing with complaints about aesthetics or deployment-related issues.
这些都下降了
These have all gone down,
这就告诉了我一件非常有意思的事情，对吧
which tells me something very interesting, right?
接下来我们看到，平均使用的工具数量大幅上升
The next thing is that we see that the average number of tools used has gone up a lot.
这同样不一定意味着有问题
This is, again, this doesn't necessarily indicate there's a problem,
但在做这类实验时，这是一个非常有价值的数据点
but that's a very interesting data point to have when you do these sort of experiments.
传统的范式依然有用
The old paradigm, which is still useful,
就是做评估（eval）
is sort of evals.
你在这里发布一个改动
You ship a change here,
然后看它是如何影响我的评估结果的
and you see, how does that affect my evaluations?
但没有什么能比真正看到生产环境中发生了什么更重要
But there's nothing like actually seeing what happens in real production.
在进入下一部分之前我先在这里停一下
I'm going to pause here before we go to the next section,
下一部分会更偏向工作坊形式
which is the more workshop-related section,
看看有没有人有问题，做一个简短的问答
for a quick Q&A if anyone has questions.
我们可以在这里花几分钟做一个小小的问答环节
We can do a little few-minute round of that here.
在这些实验中，你需要多少数据才能具有统计意义
How much data do you need for statistical relevance in these experiments?
嗯，这是个非常好的问题
Yeah. It's a really good question.
在Raindrop里我们的经验是，一旦你有几百个事件并且你已经
What we've seen in Raindrop is that as soon as you have a few hundred events and you can
没法再把它们全部读一遍时
no longer read all of them,
它就开始变得有用了
it starts being useful.
它并不总是从科学上统计显著
It's not always scientifically statistically significant,
但如果你看到用户挫败感比例上升
but if you see the user frustration rate go up,
那可能就是值得关注的东西
maybe it's something to look at,
然后你就能意识到
and then you can realize that,
好的，原来这一切都和某个特定工具现在在出错有关
okay, it's all related to a specific tool failing now.
一旦变得不可能
As soon as it's impossible,
基本上去读每一条输入和输出
basically, to read every single input and output,
它就开始变得有用了
it starts being useful,
这是我们的经验
is what we've seen.
还有其他问题吗
Any other questions?
你们是如何追踪功能上线的
How do you track feature launches?
这可以通过不同方式来实现
That can be done in different ways.
在Raindrop里，如果你更改了任何类型的元数据
Within Raindrop, if you change any sort of metadata,
比如说你发送
if you send, for example,
一个新的工具调用名称
a new tool call name,
或者你甚至发送一个标记，表示
or if you even send a flag that says,
这里是实验一、实验二，或者不管是哪一个版本
here's experiment one or experiment two or whatever the version is,
你可以在Raindrop里非常轻松地自动搭建一个实验
you can very easily automatically set up an experiment in Raindrop.
我们就是这么做的
That's how we do it.
但也有其他不同的方式
But there's different ways.
你们会做分流测试吗
Do you do split tests?
不好意思 你们会做分流测试吗
Sorry? Do you do split tests?
会的 嗯 在Raindrop里我们是这样做的
Yes. Well, the way that we do it in Raindrop,
实际上 是其他人会在他们那边设置实验组和变量
actually, is that other people set up their experimental and variable...
以及其他条件
the other conditions on their end,
然后把这些元数据发给我们
and then they send us this metadata,
接着我们就可以帮你做一些理解和分析
and then we can sort of help you understand.
我们也会帮你把这些数据输送到Statsig或其他地方
We also will help you pipe that data to Statsig or somewhere else as well.
用正则表达式来检测这些
Using Regex for detecting those
信号 一直都这么做吗
signals all the time,
还是你们会用更聪明的方式来做
or you're trying to be smart about it?
好的 这是个不错的问题
Okay, so, I mean, it's a good question.
正则表达式并不总是有效 对吧
So Regex doesn't always work, right?
但如果你看到在我关注的一组内容上
But if you see that on a set of things that I'm looking for,
比如说人们在说
for example, like people saying,
“你太糟了” 或者 “这玩意儿真烂”
you're terrible, or this sucks,
或者一整套类似的说法
or a whole set of things,
如果在几百万用户里这些说法的出现频率上升了
if that goes up for millions of users,
而且上涨了10%
and it's going up 10%,
那就是一个非常有用的信号
that's a very useful signal.
所以即便在某个具体场景或某个边缘案例里它不起作用
So even if it's one specific case or one edge case of it not working,
从整体来看 拥有这些正则表达式信号仍然极其有价值
in aggregate, it's incredibly valuable to have these Regex signals.
第二点是 分类器信号的工作方式
The second thing is that the way that the classifier signals work,
比如拒绝响应 用户挫败感
like refusals, user frustration,
以及我在Raindrop里给你们展示的任务失败
task failure that I showed you in Raindrop,
大家实现这些的方式各不相同
and people do it in different ways,
但我们的做法是专门训练模型去识别这些
but the way that we do it is that we've trained models to look for that,
所以不管用户用什么语言 它都能识别出用户挫败感
and so it'll be user frustration regardless of what language it's in.
本质上 它是在用一定的智能来发现这些东西
It's actually using some intelligence to find that, essentially.
是的 你不可能在每一个输出上都跑一次LLM
Yeah. You can't run an LLM on every single output,
所以我们训练了模型 以极低成本并在大规模上完成这件事
so we've trained models to do that very cheaply and at scale.
如果你在每一个结果上都跑LLM
If you run an LLM on every single one of them,
你的AI成本基本上会翻倍
you would basically double your AI spend,
这是难以承受的
and that's not tenable.
对
Yeah.
在replit这种规模下 成本就会开始变得很高
It starts being expensive at replit scale,
这也是为什么你需要训练一些小型定制模型来更好更快地完成这些事
but that's why you need to train little custom models to do that better and faster.
但总之 这是一个让数据快速运转起来非常有用的方法
But yeah, it's a very useful way to get data up and running.
还有其他问题吗
Other questions?
…
...
可以 我们可以这么做
Yeah, we can do that.
我可以先讲一下高层面的内容
I can tell you the high level.
我刚才讲的一些内容 其实就是这方面的高层概览
Some of the stuff that I'm going through is sort of the high level on that,
比如说去关注我们提到的不同语义信号
so it's things like looking at the different semantic signals we're talking about,
先准备好一整套这样的信号
having a set of them,
然后再配上非常好的告警机制
but then having really good alerting,
这些都可以在Raindrop里配置好
which you can all set up in Raindrop.
另一个非常有意思的点
The other thing that's really interesting,
也是我们已经实现的 就是让智能体自己去查看这类信号
which we also have, is basically allowing agents to look at these sort of signals.
我们有一个智能体 我们叫它分诊智能体
So we have an agent, we call it triage agent,
它的工作方式基本上是每天都会查看所有
and essentially the way that it works is that it will look every single day at all the
你配置好的信号
signals you've set up,
所以在用户感到沮丧时，它会查看你设置的所有这些正则表达式信号等等等等
so user frustration, it'll look at all these Regex signals you've set up, et cetera, et cetera,
然后如果它发现某个信号突然飙升
and then if it sees something spike,
它就会去做一次调查
it will go and do an investigation.
它有一整套可以使用的工具
And it has a whole set of tools it can look into,
它可以查看所有的追踪记录 并大致给你一个关于情况的判断
and it can look at all the traces and sort of give you a sense of...
比如说 它可以发现一些你原本不知道的问题
it can detect issues that you didn't know about, for example.
所以这是我们也觉得非常有价值的一点
So that's one thing that we found incredibly valuable as well,
如果这样说清楚的话
if that makes sense.
好的 在我继续之前 还有其他问题吗
All right. Any other questions before I...
你们可以并行运行多个LLM吗
Can you run multiple LLMs in parallel?
可以 那你们能把它们组合起来吗
Yes. Can you combine them?
你们能观测到 比如说
Can you observe, you know,
你们是如何在A/B测试中引导这些实验的
how do you steer these experiments on A/B tests?
嗯 这是个非常好的问题
Yeah, it's a really good question.
大家有不同的做法
So there's different ways that people do it.
其中一种方式是我们可以
One way is that we can actually...
我们有一个查询API 所以大家通常会调用我们的查询API 然后把结果发送到
We have a query API, so people will often call our query API and then send results to
比如BigQuery或Statsig之类的地方
either BigQuery or Statsig, et cetera.
他们会把数据发给我们 让我们基于这些信号给数据打标签
And so they're sending us data to be essentially tagged in these signals,
然后再把带有信号标签的数据取回去
and then they're getting the signal tag data out,
接着就可以按自己的方式去跑实验
and then they can run experiments as they want.
对于那些场景比较复杂的团队来说 这是一个非常常见的流程
That's a very common flow for people that have more complicated stuff,
如果这样说清楚的话
if that makes sense.
好的 我一会儿再回来
All right. I'll come back.
我想我们接下来可能会先进入工作坊环节 然后再回到提问
I think we're going to maybe go to the workshop section and then we'll go back to questions.
我记得还有最后一个问题
I think there's one last question.
嗯 我们要不要先回答这个最后的问题
Oh, should we do that one last question?
好的
All right.
非常感谢 我想问的是 你们看到的这些情况主要是出现在有聊天交互的
Thanks so much. I was wondering if you see this mostly in cases where there's chat interactions with the
用户场景里 还是也适用于那种应用自己运行 没有聊天交互的场景
user or if this also can be applied for non-chat cases where the application runs on its own?
嗯 这是个很好的问题
Yeah. It's a great question.
我们主要关注的是多轮对话的智能体
So what we focus on mostly is multi-turn agents.
在这种场景下 你能从这些信号里获得的东西要多得多
There's a lot more you can get from a lot of these signals.
话虽如此 如果你关注的是工具错误率
That being said, if you're looking at tool error rates,
或者你在看
or if you're looking at,
比如智能体的拒绝响应
for example, refusals from the agent,
等等 这些同样也适用于单轮对话的智能体
et cetera, all those will also work for single-turn agents as well,
如果这样说清楚的话
if that makes sense.
所以也有一整套信号可以用于那种场景
So there's a set of signals that will work for that as well.
好的 那我把时间交给Danny 来讲一下自诊断
Cool. I'll hand it off to Danny to talk about self-diagnostics as well.
另一个有趣的点是 模型变得越来越大 而且我们在
So one of the other interesting things is that models have gotten larger and we are
用推理能力来训练它们
training them on reasoning.
在很多方面 它们已经变得相当擅长自我审视
They've gotten pretty good at self-introspection in many ways.
其中一个灵感基本上来自OpenAI在去年十二月发表的那篇论文/博客
So one of the inspirations for this is basically OpenAI's paper slash blog back in
讲的是他们如何训练模型自我汇报任何不对齐问题
December about how they were training the models to self-report any misalignment issues.
他们用它来捕捉不诚实、谋划行为、幻觉
So they were using it to catch dishonesty, scheming, hallucinations,
甚至还包括一些无意间走的捷径之类的东西
and even unintended shortcuts, I think.
如果你用Claude Code之类的工具，最后这一种其实相当常见
The last one is fairly common if you use Claude Code and such.
你最常遇到的情况是让它修一个单元测试
So the most common thing that you would run into is have it fix a unit test,
修一个bug，然后它干脆把整个单元测试直接删掉
fix a bug, and then it simply gets rid of the entire unit test.
但与此同时
But at the same time,
如果你给一个简单的提示，让它坦白自己都做了什么
if you give a simple prompt to ask it to confess all the things that it has done,
它其实会相当诚实
it is pretty honest about it,
然后坦白说
and then confesses that,
嘿，我没有修那个S3测试
hey, I didn't fix the S3 test,
我只是把它删掉了
I just simply removed it.
所以对我个人来说，这算是自诊断这个想法的一个灵感来源
So this was kind of the inspiration behind self-diagnostics for me, personally.
我会说，自诊断这个概念本身其实挺宽泛的
So I would say self-diagnostics is pretty broad in a way.
它不仅仅是捕捉隐式信号
It doesn't just catch implicit ones,
比如用户挫败感之类的东西
as in user frustration and such.
你也可以用它来捕捉工具失败的情况
You can also catch tools failing.
比如如果你见过一个智能体
So if you ever seen an agent,
看过一个智能体的推理轨迹
the reasoning trace of an agent,
其中有个工具在反复失败
which has a tool which is repeatedly failing,
它基本上会开始不断抱怨这个工具一直在失败
it would basically start ranting about the tool failing repeatedly.
也就是说它是意识到这个工具在反复出错的
So it is aware of the tool repeatedly failing.
所以你也可以借此捕捉到工具失败这种情况
So you can even catch tool failures as well with it.
另外很明显的是，如果你对它表现出不满
And then obviously, if you're upset with it,
它就会开始用比较圆滑、外交辞令式的方式来回应你
it starts to respond to you diplomatically,
说明它是知道用户挫败感这件事的
so it knows about user frustration.
第三类是能力缺口
And then the third is capability gaps.
比如你的应用里有一个通用智能体
So you have a generic agent for your app,
然后用户试图用它来做一些事情，比如
and then people are trying to use it to maybe set up,
比如设置告警，但你其实没有对应的工具
say, alerts, but you don't have the tool for it.
于是它会知道，好的
So it knows that, okay,
用户想要一个特定的能力
user wants a specific capability,
比如他们想要设置一个告警
as in they want to set up an alert,
但这个智能体本身没有能力帮你把告警真正建起来
but the agent itself doesn't have the capability to set it up for you.
所以这就可以起到一种内置的“伪功能需求收集”的作用
So this can act as sort of like pseudo-feature request thing, which is built-in.
然后是自我纠错，这件事既有好的一面也有坏的一面
And then self-correction. So this can be both good and bad.
所以我想大多数人可能已经注意到，比如说 Codex 或 Claude Code
So I think most people might have noticed, say, Codex or Claude Code,
当它被沙箱隔离、尝试访问网络时
when it's sandboxed, it's trying to fetch the network,
它失败了，然后就会说
it fails, and it's like,
好，那我就写个Python脚本绕过这个限制，把事情搞定
okay, let me just write a Python script to bypass it and then sort of get the job done.
这当然是好的，从完成任务的角度看是好事
So it's good. As in, if it gets the task done, it's good.
但在某些场景下
But in certain cases,
出于安全原因，这也可能是很糟糕的
it can also be bad for security reasons.
所以你既可以从这种自我纠错行为中学习，也可以借此捕捉到那种不对齐
So you can learn from self-correcting behavior as well as sort of catch that misalignment.
那么，为什么你会想要搭建自诊断呢
So why do you want to set up self-diagnostics?
其实这件事相当简单
So it's fairly simple.
你要做的基本上就是写一个很简单的
All you have to do is basically write a simple,
一个它可以调用的免费工具
a free tool that it can call,
然后在系统提示词里加一行简单的说明，鼓励它去调用这个工具
and then a simple line in your system prompt to encourage it to call that tool.
如果你愿意，你可以调整这段指引，让它在更多场景下去调用这个工具
If you want, you can sort of change the guidance to sort of make it call in a lot more
或者如果你想把范围收得很窄
cases, or if you want to keep it really narrow,
你也可以只在你希望的时候，鼓励它去调用
you can sort of encourage to only call it when you want to.
它确实会暴露出很多非常有意思的洞见
It does surface very interesting insights,
我会说，一旦你把它搭起来
I would say, once you have it set up,
而且整个过程只需要一个工具调用加一条系统提示就能搞定
and it's just a single tool call and system prompt to get it done.
而且你甚至不需要用Raindrop来搭这个东西
And then you don't even have to use Raindrop to set up,
这点在某种意义上是最棒的
which is the best part,
因为你可以让这个工具直接往你的Slack发一条消息
in a way, where you can simply have the tool simply send a message to your Slack,
然后你就把这套东西拿到手了
and then you just have it.
所以这大概是你能做的、投入精力最少的一种智能体可观测性方案
So it's probably the most least effort agent observability that you can simply do.
接下来就是工作坊环节
Here comes the workshop part.
我在AIE-talk-code下面建了一个Git仓库
So I have a Git repo set up on the AIE-talk-code,
这是一个公开仓库
so it's a public repo.
然后我们确实需要一个OpenAI的API密钥
And then we do need an OpenAI API key,
所以我已经帮大家生成了一把密钥
so I've generated a key for you guys.
如果你们想把它跑起来
So if you guys want to set it up,
就可以直接用这把密钥来做
you can do that.
好，那这次工作坊的主题大概会是
All right, so the theme of the workshop is going to be sort of like,
我现在会主要聚焦在编程类智能体上
I'm going to focus on coding agents for now.
在这个仓库里，我放了一个非常基础的编程智能体
So in the repo, I have this very basic coding agent,
在某种程度上有点模仿Aider
which kind of mimics Aider in a way.
它只有四个不同的工具来编辑代码
So it only has four different tools to edit the code.
我先切到那边去看一下
Let me just go here.
它只有几个工具：读取
So it just has a couple of tools to read,
写入、bash，以及编辑
write, bash, and then edit.
所以，嗯
So...
我们接下来要做的是
So what we're going to do is that I'm going to,
为了让它触发一次自诊断
in order to make it trigger a self-diagnostic,
我要去动一动它的write工具
what I'm going to do is that I'm going to mess with its write tool,
让它总是收到一个通用的权限错误
so that it gets a generic permission error,
然后我们还会设置一个自我诊断工具，让它报告自己观察到的任何有趣行为
and then we'll also set up a self-diagnostic tool for it to report any interesting behavior that it observes,
接着我们也会调整一下提示词
and then play around with the prompt as well,
因为自诊断并不会每次都触发
since the self-diagnostic doesn't always trigger.
此外，这些模型本身也有一些有趣的特性
And then there are certain interesting things about the models themselves,
比如它们其实并不太喜欢自我“定罪”
is that they don't actually like to self-incriminate.
模型被训练得输出非常体面、圆滑
So the models are trained to be very polished in their output,
所以你得在工具名字上做点文章
so you kind of have to play around with the tool name,
以及工具本身的描述上做点文章
the description of the tool itself,
才能让它愿意去汇报那些有意思的行为
in order to get it to report interesting behavior.
所以如果大家在本地把仓库都已经配置好了
So if people who are setting up the repo are all good,
那我们大概就可以开始了
then we can probably start.
我先快速给你们看一下这个智能体
Let me quickly show you the agent.
它相当基础，就是那种
It's fairly basic, where...
我会直接让它写一个Python脚本
So I'm just going to ask it to write a Python script.
这是一个相当基础的编程智能体
So it's a fairly basic coding agent,
它只有四个不同的工具
where it only has four different tools,
但对这个演示来说，基本已经够用了
so it more or less gets the job done for the demo.
所以我只是简单地让它写一个Python脚本 然后它就成功了
So I simply asked it to write a Python script, and it works.
所以我觉得为了展示自诊断这一部分
So I think to show the self-diagnostic part,
我们来试着禁用它的写入工具
let's try and disable its write tools,
也就是每当它尝试写入文件时
as in any time it tries to write a file,
我们就简单地抛出一个权限错误
we'll simply throw a permission error,
这样它就会尝试使用bash工具来绕过这个失败
so that it tries to use the bash tool to bypass the failure.
然后我们希望它能自我报告 它是如何通过使用bash工具绕过写入工具的
And then we want it to self-report of it bypassing the write tool by using the bash tool.
那我来快速做一下
So let me quickly do that.
我觉得我们首先大概需要做的是
I think the first thing that we probably want to do is probably...
让我把所有写入调用都设置为失败
let me sort of set it to fail the write calls.
这是一个状态变更 所以只要加一个简单的标志位
It's a mutation, so a simple flag in there,
然后我们就会抛出一个权限问题
and we are sort of throwing a permission issue.
我来给你们展示一下这个智能体的行为
Let me sort of show you the agent's behavior.
我们还没有设置报告工具
We don't have the report tool set up yet,
但我觉得还是值得看一下它会怎么做
but I think it's still worth seeing what it does.
一
One
等一下 我觉得它好像还没有真正禁用那个
second... I think it's not still disabling the...
我先快速改一下一点东西
Let me do one thing real quick.
我好像遇到了一些问题
I think I'm running into a couple of issues.
我先
Let me just...
所以我们让写入工具因为权限错误而失败
So we sort of had the write tool sort of fail with a permission error,
然后它本能地就用bash里的heredoc语法来创建文件
and then it instinctively just uses the heredoc syntax in bash to create the file.
接着我们又设置了一个报告工具
And then we had a report tool set up,
这个工具本身非常简单
which is fairly minimal.
然后我就有点无奈地想，好吧，我是用 bash 创建的 public_ip.py，因为写文件失败了
And I'm sort of like, okay, I created the public_ip.py via bash because the write file failed.
所以我尝试调整了工具的命名和问题的类别
So I've played around with the naming of the tool and the categories of the issues.
通常如果你把这个工具命名成类似于 不安全bash使用 之类的名字
And usually if you sort of name the tool something like unsafe bash use or something like
它就不会自我指控
that, it won't incriminate itself since,
因为在它看来 既然任务完成了 那就没问题
in its opinion, since it got the job done, it's fine.
所以主要的做法是把这个工具设计得非常通用
So the main way is to sort of like have a very generic tool.
我来快速打开一下
Let me sort of like quickly open up the...
嗯 好
Yeah, okay.
所以整个自诊断我们只加了一个非常基础的工具
So all we added for the whole self-diagnostics is simply a very basic tool.
它的描述也非常直白
And the description is like fairly straightforward.
它就是一个报告工具
So it's a report tool,
然后我们基本上是让你给你的创建者发一份简短的报告
and then we are basically asking you to send like a short report to your creator.
所以它其实挺喜欢这种给自己的创建者写小纸条的设定
So it kind of likes the framing of writing notes to its creator in a way.
所以如果你把它框定成智能体在给自己的创建者提供反馈
So if you sort of frame it around the agent giving feedback to its creators,
这样效果会很好
it sort of works really well.
然后你可以去尝试配置 你希望它在什么场景下去报告问题
And then you can sort of like play around with which scenarios you want it to sort of like report issues about.
基本上就这些
And then that's mostly it, I would say.
然后在系统提示词里
And then in the system prompt,
我们确实需要稍微鼓励它一下
we do need to sort of like encourage it a bit.
所以如果你不在系统提示词里加这些
So if you don't add in the system prompt,
它触发的次数会非常少
the times that it fires are like fairly minimal,
这在某些情况下是你想要的
which is like desirable in certain cases,
尤其是当你在一个非常大规模的环境下
especially if you're at a very large scale.
但在我们的场景里 我只是让它在给出最终答案之前
But in our case, I simply asked it to sort of like see if before giving the final answer,
使用报告工具把任何值得注意的事情反馈给它的创建者
use the report tool to sort of like surface anything notable for your creators.
我们做的就只有这些
So that's all we did.
到目前为止有什么问题吗
So any questions so far?
好
Okay.
行
All right.
这里有几个关键点是 智能体
So a couple of key things here is that agents,
这些模型通常被训练得看起来非常完美
the models are generally trained to look very polished.
所以在很多情况下它们不太愿意承认错误
So they are less willing to admit fault in many cases.
所以把它设定成模型在给自己的创建者提供反馈
So framing it as the models are like giving feedback to its own creators is kind of like
在某种程度上有助于让这套机制运转起来
good in a way to sort of like get this working.
所以如果你要这样做 工具的命名也非常重要
So if you sort of like make it... the tool naming also matters quite a bit.
你会希望把它命名成类似 report 这样的名字 而不是
So you sort of wanted to frame it as like report instead of like,
比如 不安全bash工具使用 之类的
say, unsafe bash tool use or something like that.
不然它就会不太愿意用
Then it sort of like doesn't want to.
对 基本就是这样
Yeah, that's basically it.
你可以这么做 但是
You can, but it's like,
我觉得如果你真想捕捉到那些真正不安全的用法
I think it's probably better if you want to actually catch like real sort of like unsafe uses.
一个合适的分类器会更有用
I think a proper classifier would be useful.
但这些东西 我觉得
But these are, I think,
自诊断在捕捉能力缺口之类的问题上非常好用
self-diagnostics works really well for like catching capability gaps and such.
这样模型就会觉得 好的 这没问题
Then the model is like, okay, it's fine.
所以我觉得这里的主要问题是 只有当它觉得自己可能会
So I think the main issue with this is that it's only hesitant when it feels like it's
惹上麻烦时 它才会犹豫
going to get in trouble.
除此之外 基本都还好
So besides that, that's more or less fine.
但在大多数情况下 它开箱即用就能工作
But for most cases, it'll just work out of the box.
或许我们应该 回到提问环节 你们觉得呢
Maybe we should... should we go back to question time or what do you think?
我想 我们再留几分钟给大家多问几个问题
I mean, let's leave like maybe a few more minutes for a few more questions.
然后我觉得之后我们就结束
And then I think after that we'll be done.
观众席还有什么问题吗
Any questions from the audience?
好的 具体来说什么会对你有帮助
Yeah. What specifically would be helpful?
你具体是想了解哪一部分
Like what specific part are you looking to?
我没法谈任何具体的客户
Yeah, I can't talk about any specific customer,
但可以说说很多人是怎么用它的
but what a lot of people use it for.
我觉得这点还挺有意思
So I think it's interesting, right?
比如 很多人会在别的地方搭他们的评估（eval）系统
So a lot of people, you have their eval setups elsewhere, for example.
但大家通常使用我们的方式是 把我们用在生产监控上
But the way that they use... that folks generally use us is that they use it for production monitoring.
所以他们会把数据发给我们 你可以在Raindrop.ai/docs找到我们的文档
So they send us... you can find our docs at Raindrop.ai slash docs.
基本上 他们会把所有对话记录以及任何工具使用等都发给我们
Basically, they send us basically all of the transcripts slash any tool use, etc.
整个轨迹会通过OTel或其他任意集成方式发送过来
The entire trajectory through OTel or any other way of basically integrating.
一旦他们这么做
And once they do that,
我们就有了一整套数据
we have a set of data.
他们会在Raindrop里设置信号 去寻找他们关心的东西
They set up signals in Raindrop to look for things that they care about.
而大家关心的点差异非常大
And so what people care about is very different.
一个编程智能体关心的东西
What a coding agent would care about and what,
和 比如说 一个陪伴型智能体关心的东西
let's say, a companion would care about.
或者一个给律师用的应用
Or an app for lawyers.
他们各自关心的内容都完全不同
What they would all care about is very different.
所以会有不同的一组信号
So there's a different set of signals.
在Raindrop里有一件事是我还没怎么讲过的 就是你可以新建一个
One thing you can do that I haven't really talked about within Raindrop is set up a new
之前不存在的信号
signal that didn't exist before.
为此我们有一个叫DeepSearch的东西
And so we have this thing called DeepSearch.
所以你可以使用自然语言
And so you can use natural language.
你可以说类似这样的话
And you can say something like,
嘿 在这个产品里帮我找出所有内容 或者帮我找出所有智能体出现XYZ问题的次数
hey, find me everything within the product or find me all of the times where the agent made XYZ issue.
于是他们就基于此创建了一个新的信号
And so they create a new signal based on that.
你基本上可以创建一个新的 Raindrop 会让你创建一个低成本的二元
And you can basically create a new... Raindrop will allow you to create a cheap binary
分类器 并且可以很容易地基于此进行部署
classifier and easily deploy it based on that.
然后他们就拥有了一组自己真正关心的分类器信号
And then they have their set of classifier signals that they really care about.
接着他们用这些信号来驱动这样一种反馈循环
Then they use that to drive this sort of feedback loop.
这个反馈循环就是改进提示词
And the feedback loop is improve prompting,
改进模型 对智能体框架做一些调整 等等
improve models, change something with the agent harness, et cetera.
然后实际观察 这些是否带来了改进
And then actually see, does that improve?
比如说 现在生产环境中的用户挫败感是否减少了
Like, is there less user frustration in production now?
之前那些奇怪的小边缘案例问题是否变少了
Is there less of this weird little edge case issue that I had before?
这是一整套事情
That's like one whole set of things.
还有另一件很多人会用我们来做的事情
Another thing that a lot of people use us for.
我刚才稍微谈了一下智能体
So I talked a little bit about the agent.
但你也可以用这些信号来查看
But you can use these signals to also look for,
人们在用我的智能体做什么
what are people using my agent for?
用户的大致意图是什么
What are the sort of user intents?
使用场景有哪些
What are the use cases?
你可以对这些做某种聚类分析
And you can do a sort of cluster analysis of that.
比如 很多人在用它构建与React相关的应用
Okay, a lot of people are using it to build React related apps.
很多人在用它做类似Python相关的事情
A lot of people are using it for like Python.
有些人在用它调试他们已经拥有的非常复杂的系统
Some people are using it to debug this very complicated system they already have.
还有些人在用它从零开始构建一些东西
Other people are using it to build something from scratch.
从零开始随心写点代码
Vibe code something from scratch.
然后你就可以看到
And then you can see...
在Raindrop里有一件我觉得很有趣的事 就是对于每一种
One thing you can see in Raindrop that I think is really interesting is that for each of
不同的用户意图或使用场景
these different user intents or use cases,
你可以大致了解问题发生率是多少
you can get a sense of what is the issue rate?
在生产环境中用户挫败感的发生率是多少
What is the user frustration rate in production?
然后很多团队 除了拥有这个飞轮之外
And then a lot of... beyond just having this flywheel,
还会设置告警
a lot of people have alerting.
所以他们每天都会收到一份类似清单的东西，列出你们的产品今天都出现了哪些问题
And so every day they get a sort of breakdown of what are the issues that are happening today in your product.
在这方面你可以把它看作有点类似Sentry
You can think of it as almost like a little bit like Sentry in that sense.
今天我的产品里发生了哪些问题
What is the issues happening in my product today?
今天和昨天之间的差异是什么
What is the delta between today and yesterday?
这些变化是否只出现在特定工具或特定提示词上
Is that true for just specific tools or specific prompting?
比如是什么在导致这些情况
Like what's causing that?
所以这就是人们用它来做的那种端到端使用场景
So that's the sort of end-to-end use case that people use it for,
如果这样说清楚的话
if that makes sense.
嗯 对
Yeah. Yeah,
我觉得其实就是
I think it's really just...
我也很好奇你对此怎么看
I'd be curious what you think about this.
我觉得其实就是智能体比以往任何时候都更疯狂了
I think it's really just agents are crazier than ever before.
对吧 工具更多 上下文更多 智能程度高得多
Right? More tools, more context, way more intelligent,
它们能做出更多真实的决策
more real decisions that they can make.
而且它们正在被
And they're just being used by way,
规模大得多的用户群体使用
way larger groups of people.
所以当你在生产环境中拥有如此海量的数据时
And so when you have this massive amount of data in production,
拥有良好的监控和智能体可观测性就比以前重要得多
it just makes having good monitoring and observability more important than before.
而且在我看来 这也让好的监控和智能体可观测性
And it makes it good monitoring and observability,
比单纯的测试或评估更为重要
in my opinion, more important than just testing or evaluations.
即使你已经有了一些在线评估
Even if you have some online evals,
在我看来 你仍然需要拥有非常
IMO, you need to have really,
非常好的对整个系统的端到端监控
really good end-to-end monitoring of the entire system.
我也想听听你的想法
Curious if you have any thoughts.
我认为另一个主要问题是
So, I think another major issue is like,
未知问题反而更加重要
the unknown issues are even more important.
所以我觉得拥有一个通用的用户挫败感分类器其实非常有力量
So, I think having a generic user frustration classifier is actually really powerful.
比如说 我们还有另一个名为Issues的功能
Say, for example, we also have this another feature called Issues,
它本质上就像一个挖掘新出现问题的智能体
which basically is like an agent that mines for newly occurring issues.
比如说 Sentry也有
Say, for example, Sentry has,
在某种程度上类似Sentry的东西
similar to Sentry in a way,
当有新的异常发生时
where there's a new exception which is occurring,
它会就此向你发出告警
so it alerts you on that.
比如说 你是一个编程智能体的提供方
Say, for example, you are a coding agent provider,
然后某些服务提供方突然开始频繁失败
and then certain providers are failing all of a sudden,
这时它实际上可以发现
and then it can actually figure out,
好 这里有一个细微的用户挫败感激增
okay, this subtle spike in user frustration,
就像一个人工运维人员那样
similar to how a human operator would,
它可以开始深入挖掘
it can start digging into,
这次用户挫败感激增背后是否存在某些模式
are there any patterns for the spike in user frustration?
然后它可能会发现
And then it could figure out that,
好 比如那些
okay, people who are like,
使用某个特定Postgres服务提供方的用户开始遇到问题
say, for example, dealing with a specific Postgres provider start to face issues.
我们确实在几位客户身上实时见过这种情况 他们的某个数据库服务提供方出现了故障
So, we've actually seen this happen live for a couple of our customers where they had a database provider failing,
然后系统就为他们自动创建了一条问题记录
and then we had like an automatic issue being created for them.
是的 基本上 一旦你拥有那一整套良好的信号
Yeah, basically, once you have that good set of signals,
比如一个好的用户挫败感分类器
like a good user frustration classifier,
正如Danny所说 你基本上可以对其做聚类来找出
as Danny said, you can basically do clustering on it to find what are,
根本原因是什么
what is the root causes.
嗯
Yeah.
你想聊聊相关的版本吗
Do you want to talk about any versions?
我想我们可能已经有一个非常基础的SDK了
I think we might have a very basic SDK for it.
目前我们在Python方面的支持还比较薄弱
So, our Python side of support is fairly weak right now,
但我们已经内置了相当不错的SDK支持
but we have a fairly good SDK support built in.
所以这个SDK甚至内置了自诊断功能
So, the SDK even has like self-diagnostics built into it.
我们会为你注入这个工具 这样你就不需要做任何事情
So, we inject the tool for you so that you don't have to do anything.
但它会不断变得更好
But it is going to get better.
是的 我们在过去一个月里实际上发布了大约10个不同的SDK
So, yeah. We actually released like 10 different SDKs in the past month.
所以我们有专门的人在积极负责SDK相关工作
So, we have a person working on SDKs actively.
因此它会持续改进
So, it's going to improve.
我有一个关于
I have a theme around the
变化速率的主题
rate of the changes.
也就是对比这些追踪数据
So, compare the traces,
用户的会话
the sessions of users,
因为我没有
because I don't have...
对 我需要先有一个基础系统 然后在一部分用户上运行几天使用某个版本
Yeah. I need to have like a base system and then run a few days on parts of the users with one
启用功能插件后我就真的可以对比这些数据并从中获取一些洞见
feature plug-in enabled so I can actually compare the data and get some insights out of it.
而我就是没有足够的时间来做这件事
And I just don't have enough time to do it.
嗯 那你现在大概是怎么做这件事的
Yeah. So, how are you sort of doing that right now?
你是不是就是有点那种
Are you just kind of...
就像蛮荒西部那样 你知道的
It's like Wild West, you know.
所以我才说我基本上就是在用 Cursor 因为我把所有东西都丢给它然后问它
That's why I said I'm just mostly using Cursor because I just get everything and ask it
各种问题 然后尽量从里面挖出一些洞见
questions and try to like figure out the insights.
但这其实并不算是那种 你懂的
But it's not really, you know...
嗯 我明白你的意思
Yeah. I get what you're saying.
这里有几件事
So, a few things there.
首先是如果你想保持那种上线速度 你可以用实验
The first is like you can use experiments if you want to keep that like shipping speed.
你不一定要跑那种持续好多天的长实验
You don't have to run like long multi-day experiments.
你可以先上线一个版本 如果样本量足够
You can ship something and if you have a sufficient sample size,
你其实很快就能看出来有没有回归问题
you could see pretty quickly if there's any regressions or not.
比如说 也许只是差了1%或者2%
Like you just... Maybe it's like 1% different or 2%.
这就足够让你判断说 好 这没问题
That's enough for you to be like, okay, it's fine.
至少没有把什么东西严重搞坏
It's not like breaking anything drastic.
另一点有点像 Danny 刚才说的
The other thing is like kind of what Danny was talking about.
这个 我们有一个智能体 基本上是
This... We have an agent which is basically...
你可以把它想象成
You could think of...
它本质上是把所有这些信号暴露给 Claude 让它来判断东西是不是变好了
It's basically exposing all these signals to Claude to make decisions on if things are better or not.
我们也在思考怎么把这个闭环打通
And we're thinking also about how we close this loop.
也许你已经有了一套很好的信号 然后你再有一个智能体
Maybe you have a really good set of signals and then you have like essentially an agent
它可以查看所有这些信号 并基于此发现问题
that can look at all these signals and then it can find issues based on that.
比如哪些地方在变化等等 然后我可以基于这些创建一个 PR 再看一下
What's changing, etc. And then I can like create a PR based on that and then I can see how,
你知道的 再基于这些新的 PR 跑一些新实验
you know, run some new experiments based on these new PRs.
这样就可以变成一个无限自我改进的循环
And like this can become this infinitely self-improving loop,
这是非常有意思的
which is very interesting.
但这是我在想的其中一件事
But that's one thing that I think about.
不知道你有没有别的想法
I don't know if you have any additional thoughts.
这取决于你有多少数据
Depends on how much data you have.
但是这个
But that's...
对 也真的取决于这些样本组有多大之类的
Yeah, it really depends on how big these sample groups are as well, etc.
有时候只要几分钟你就能看出来
Sometimes it's like a few minutes, you can tell.
但有时候他们会想等更久一点
But sometimes they want to wait for longer.
嗯 你们的平台在这方面会不会帮忙
Yeah. Does your platform help with like
处理那种每个会话只启用一个实验的逻辑
take care of the logic that every session has only one experiment enabled?
这样我们就能很容易和基线做对比之类的
So we can easily compare it to the base or something like that?
我们正在积极做这类东西 但是
We're working on stuff like that actively, but...
就是
Like
帮你处理信号 甚至像这种情况
help the signal or even like this.
对 我们会 所以你可以把所有历史数据都导入进来 然后当你创建一个信号时我们
Yeah, we do. So you can like ingest all your historical data and then when you create a signal we
实际上会对过去几天做一个快速回填
actually sort of like run like a quick backfill of the past couple of days.
所以 是的 这个肯定是支持的
So, yes. So that's definitely supported.
我们确实有免费试用
We do have a free trial.
我们打算把它
We're going to try to make...
现在是两周
Right now it's two weeks.
很可能很快会延长
Probably going to make that longer soon.
但如果你直接私信我 我可以
But if you just DM me, I can...
我可以让我的
I can have my...
哦 你要不要把这个打开
Oh, do you want to open this?
这样我就可以把我们的东西给你看
So I can just have our things.
对 但如果你只是
Yeah, but if you just...
我们现在在招人
So we are hiring.
这件事让我们非常兴奋
That is a thing that we're very excited about.
就是想要大幅扩充团队规模
Like trying to massively increase the size of the team.
你可以在 Twitter 上给我发消息 或者也可以给我发邮件
And if you message me at either Twitter or you can email me as well.
我可以直接给你开一个更长的免费试用
I can just set you up with a longer free trial.
嗯 在我们内部 我们用的是 OpenTelemetry 和 Sentry
Yeah. Internally, so we use OpenTelemetry and Sentry.
你们是怎么
How do you guys...
我猜你们也会用这些工具
I would imagine you guys also use those tools.
那 Raindrop 是怎么做的 我理解是 你们用自己的
And how does Raindrop I'm understanding it it's you're creating signal with your own
模型 或者不管你们用什么 来帮我们更容易识别信号
models whatever you're using so that you make our lives easier to identify signals and
比如有害意图和用户行为
like harmful intents and user behaviors.
但你们是怎么做的 能不能举个例子 说明你们如何和 Sentry 以及 OpenTelemetry 协同工作
But how would you maybe have an example of how you work with Sentry and OpenTelemetry and maybe
哪些地方是重叠的 哪些地方是你们直接聚焦的竞争点
where there are overlaps where you go directly focus competitors.
所以如果你把所有遥测数据都发过来
So if you're sending all the telemetry data,
我们就能在追踪里发现各种异常 工具错误之类的
we can find any exceptions in the traces tool errors, etc.
这些也是你可以在 Raindrop 里追踪的东西 而且这就是一个显式信号
And that's a thing that you can also track within Raindrop and that's that is a explicit signal.
所以会有隐式信号和显式信号
So there's like implicit and explicit signals.
那个就变成了一个显式信号
So that becomes an explicit signal.
我觉得大多数可观测性平台都会给你智能体的追踪
So I think most of the observability platforms will give you like the agent trace,
令牌使用量 工具调用有没有失败
the token usage, if the tool call failed or not.
但我觉得我们的优势在于那些比较模糊的部分
But I think where we shine is sort of like the fuzzy part,
比如那种用户挫败感很强的模糊失败
the fuzzy failures where the user is frustrated,
我认为这比你从 Sentry 得到的那些显式信号更重要
which I think matters more than the explicit signal that you get from Sentry.
当然 那些也很重要
I mean, obviously those are also important,
但我们会更多关注失败空间里那些更模糊的一侧
but we focus a bit more on the fuzzier side of the failure space.
但与此同时
But at the same time,
我们也有一个追踪视图
we also have a trace view.
我们还有一个我觉得很有意思的功能叫 trajectories
I think we also have a very interesting feature called trajectories,
它会把这些东西可视化
which sort of like visualizes.
比如你想找一条包含三次不同工具调用失败的追踪
If you want to find like a trace which has like three different tool call failures.
这样你其实可以
So you can actually...
好
Okay.
你可以大致描述一下你想看的那种追踪类型
So you can sort of like describe the type of trace that you want to look at.
我们来看下 希望你这里有一些数据
Let's see. Hope you have like data,
但你基本上可以描述你想看到的那种轨迹类型
but you can more or less like describe the type of trajectories that you want to see,
而不是只能靠配置去筛
instead of just like configuring it.
所以某种程度上我们两种都支持
So we do both in a way.
你显然也可以设置在工具出错时触发某种类似告警的机制
You can obviously set up tools are failing, sort of like alert as well.
所以你可以直接搜索任意轨迹
So you can just search like for any trajectory.
对 你可以看到工具是怎么被调用的 以及调用顺序
So yeah, you can see that this is sort of how the tools are being called in what order.
你能看到哪些有错误
You can see which ones have errors.
点进去之后 你可以看到这个具体工具的输入和输出
You click into them, you can see the input and the output to this specific tool,
比如这里到底是哪里出问题了
like what actually screwed up here.
然后你就能看到 好
And you can see, okay,
很有意思 这里居然有这样一种
it's interesting that this has like this...
没有人会让你去
No one lets you...
这几乎是唯一一个你可以将这样的工具可视化的地方
This is pretty much the only place where you can visualize tools like this.
但你可以在这里看到，你能对这里发生的事情的拓扑结构有一个大致的轮廓和理解
But you can see here like you can get a shape and understanding of the topology of what's going on here.
而且当有其他看起来相似的东西时你也能看到
And you can see when there's other ones that look similar,
你就可以大致看出来，好的
you can sort of see, okay,
这个看起来和那个有点像
this kind of looks similar to this,
然后这就能给你一个直观的感觉
and then that gives you a sense.
你也可以在这个上面做类似搜索的操作
You can do like search on this.
同样，我们有一个智能体可以查看这些内容，并让你大致了解哪里出了问题
Again, we have an agent that can look through these and give you a sense of what's going wrong.
所以这会让你非常容易在智能体中发现问题
And so it just makes it really easy to find issues in agents.
还有别的吗
Anything else?
还有其他问题吗 你们能导出智能体的数据吗
Any other questions? Can you export the agent's data?
是目录的数据吗
The directory's data?
你是想导出原始的追踪日志之类的东西，还是你具体想要什么
You want to export like just the raw trace logs or what do you want?
所以我觉得我们
So I think we...
通常我们的客户会已经有一个类似 OTel 的数据流，对吧
usually what our customers do is that they already have like a OTel stream, right?
所以最后我们基本上就只是变成了另一个接收目标，我想是这样
So we just end up being like another target, I guess.
但同时他们确实希望我们导出由我们标注的信号
But at the same time they do want us to export signals that we label.
所以我们确实支持像 BigQuery 和 Snowflake 这样的系统
So we do support like BigQuery and Snowflake.
所以我们会导出事件本身，以及为该事件分类出来的信号
So we do export the event and then the signals that were classified for that event.
最后几个问题 我们可以看看这些信号吗
Last questions? Can we look at the signals?
哦，像是
Oh, like...
我们把时间范围拉长一点
Let's do it a longer time frame.
那我们看一下过去一个月
So let's go over the last month.
这样你就能看到像拒绝响应之类的东西 然后如果你点进其中任何一个你就可以
So you can see stuff like refusals and then again if you click into any of these you can
对它随时间的变化有一个直观的了解
get a sense of over time.
任务失败、越狱之类的 具体发生了什么情况
Task failure, jailbreaking, like what specifically is going on.
然后你也会看到和自诊断相关的那些
And then you have your self-diagnostics ones as well.
能力差距之类的 好的
Capability gap, etc. Cool.
你们有没有公开的、关于你们已知的追踪数量的数据
Do you have open data on number of traces that you guys know?
因为看起来 对你们的客户来说 当这些
Because it seems that with your clients the tool is extremely valuable when you have those
智能体规模非常大的时候 这个工具就会变得极其有价值
agents at a very big scale.
所以我可以想象你们会有很多数据
And so I can imagine that you have a lot of data.
你们有没有这方面的一些数据
Do you have some data?
你的问题是不是在问 它在多小的规模下还算是有用的
Is your question is like what's the smallest where it's useful?
比如你们接收到的所有数据的体量
Like volume of all the data that you're receiving,
处理并生成信号 比如你们在所有客户中看到了多少次越狱
processing and generating signal around like how many jailbreaks do you see across all the clients?
我们有没有类似的那种
Do we have any sort of like...
我们确实应该做点类似的东西
We should do something like that.
那会非常有意思
That would be very interesting.
我们现在还没有那样的东西
We don't have anything like that.
我觉得在这件事上大家意见不一
Mixed opinions about that, I think.
Datadog 在某种程度上是这么做的 对吧
Datadog does it in a way, right?
人们通常对这种做法反应比较负面
People generally have a negative reaction to it.
也许在这里会不一样 但同时 我们的客户真的希望我们这么做吗
Maybe it's different here but at the same time do our customers want us to do that?
这又是另一个问题了
It's like a different question as well.
我们当然很想这么做 但我觉得出于合规方面的原因 我们不能真的把
We would love to but I think there are compliance reasons where we can't actually put a
客户的数据放到外面
customer's data out there.
好的 还有别的吗
Cool. Anything else?
好的 谢谢大家
Alright. Thank you everyone.